Let's start with nextjs, you can simply google for nextjs and then pick the github repository
NextJs ile balayalm, sadece nextjs iin google ve daha sonra bulduunuz
link you find. On this page you'll find detailed instructions on how to use it,
github deposu balantsn seebilirsiniz. Bu sayfada, nasl kullanlaca hakknda ayrntl talimatlar,
a link leading to another page where you can dive even deeper into it and also instructions how to
daha derinlere inebileceiniz baka bir sayfaya ynlendiren bir balant ve ayrca nasl kurulacana
install it.
dair talimatlar bulacaksnz.
But what is nextjs?
Ama nextjs nedir?
Here it's saying nextjs is a minimalistic framework for a server rendered react applications.
te burada nextjs, sunucu tarafndan oluturulan tepki uygulamalar iin minimal bir ereve.
Now server side rendering is quite an advanced react concept,
imdi sunucu taraf oluturma olduka gelimi bir tepki konseptidir,
there are therefore courses focusing entirely on that.
bu nedenle tamamen buna odaklanan kurslar vardr.
In a nutshell, server side rendering simply means that when a user enters a URL leading to your react
zetle, sunucu taraf oluturma ilemi, bir kullanc sizin tepki uygulamanza veya tepki
app or one of your pages of your react app, it will pre-render that page on the server so that the
uygulamanzn sayfalarndan birine ynlendiren bir URL girdiinde, bu sayfay sunucuda nceden oluturduundan,
server returns that pre-rendered html code,
sunucunun nceden oluturulduu anlamna gelir html kodu, ne
let me show you what I mean.
demek istediimi gstereyim.
If we have a look at our normal setup,
Normal kurulumumuza bakacak olursak,
we have a server and a client
bir sunucu ve bir
and of course our react app code and with that, I mean both the build code in this build folder we had
mterimiz var ve tabi ki bizim uygulama kodu ve buna tepki veriyoruz, yani bu
in that create react app application and also the raw code in your source folder.
uygulama klasrnde hem derleme uygulamas oluturduk hem de bu uygulamada tepki uygulamas uygulamas oluturuyoruz. Kaynak klasrnzdeki kodu.
If you now visit your server for the first time, so you load the page for the first time, the server would
Sunucunuzu ilk kez ziyaret ediyorsanz, sayfay ilk kez yklerseniz,
typically ship you the index.html file and your code and then you would load it as a single page application
sunucu genellikle dizini size gnderir. html dosyas ve kodunuz ve daha sonra bunu istemcinizde tek
in your client.
bir sayfa uygulamas olarak yklersiniz.
The problem can be that if your page needs to be crawlable by search engines, crawlers like the google
Sorun u ki, sayfanzn arama motorlar tarafndan taranabilmesi gerekiyorsa, google taraycs gibi tarayclar, zellikle
crawler might not really understand or read your page correctly, especially if you are using asynchronous
de ilk ierii yklemek iin senkronize olmayan kod kullanyorsanz, sayfanz doru
code to load the initial content.
bir ekilde anlayamayabilir veya okuyamayabilir.
So if you have a page where the first thing you do in javascript is you reach out to a server and then
Eer javascript'te yaptnz ilk eyin, bir sunucuya ulatnz bir sayfa varsa
render the results to the screen when the data is back,
ve verileri geri dndnzde sonular
that might happen super fast to the user but the crawler will only see the spinner or whatever you are
kullancya dndrdnzde, kullanc iin sper hzl olabilir ancak tarayc sadece spinner veya veriler
showing until the data is there.
orada olana kadar gsterdiiniz her ey.
Now with server side rendering, for the first page load which is always what the crawler sees,
Artk sunucu taraf oluturma ileminde, taraycnn grd her zaman ilk sayfa yklemesi iin
the server will fetch and render the react app so it won't just fetch and return it,
sunucu tepki programn getirecek ve ileyecektir, bylece yalnzca alma ve geri gndermeyecek, ayn
it also renders it for that page you visited and then it returns that pre-rendered page along with the
zamanda ziyaret ettiiniz sayfa iin de gsterecektir. nceden oluturulmu bu sayfay tepki uygulama paketi ile birlikte dndrr,
react app bundle so that from this point on, you still have a single page application
bylece bu noktadan sonra hala tek bir sayfa uygulamasna sahip olursunuz, bylece daha
so you then still work as before.
nce olduu gibi alrsnz.
It's just about that initial page load essentially, now nextjs is a package helping you with server
Esasen bu ilk sayfa yklemesi ile ilgilidir, imdi nextjs sunucu taraf oluturma ileminde size yardmc olan
side rendering because that is super tricky to set up.
bir pakettir, nk kurulumu ok zor.
And besides just helping you with it, it gives you a custom or a specific structure to work in.
Ve sadece size yardmc olmann yan sra, size almak iin bir zel veya belirli bir yap verir.
This structure takes advantage of enforcing a strict folder structure you have to use
Bu yap, kullanmanz gereken sk bir klasr yapsn kullanmann avantajn kullanr,
though we're only talking about one folder mainly which has to be named in a certain way, so that all
ancak sadece belirli bir ekilde adlandrlmas gereken bir klasrden bahsederiz, bylece
the routes of your application are actually generated automatically.
uygulamanzn tm yollar otomatik olarak oluturulur.
Let me show you what I mean and how we start such a nextjs project over the nextjs lectures.
Ne demek istediimi ve gelecek derslerde nasl bir sonraki projeye balayacamz gstereyim.